A Guide to the Charles Franklin Baldwin Papers, 1816, and 1940-1984
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Charles Franklin Baldwin Papers 1916, and 1940-1984
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10700
This collection consists of ca. 125 items (2 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Honorable Charles F. Baldwin of Cockeysville, Maryland, gave his papers to the Library on September 3, 1986.
Scope and Content
This collection of the papers of former United States Ambassador Charles Franklin Baldwin (1902-), 1916, and 1940-1984, consists of ca. 125 items (2 Hollinger boxes). It contains correspondence, speeches and articles by Baldwin, printed material, newsclippings about his career, a copy of his memoir, An Ambassador's Journey, and a separate addendum to the memoir.
Correspondents include: Richard V. Allen, Chester Bowles, Paul E. Bruehl, John Foster Dulles, Mary Gould Elliott, J. W. Fulbright, Francis J. Galbraith, Ralph Graves, Loy W. Henderson, Jim Langley, Louis Mountbatten (of Burma), B. K. Nehru, Richard Nixon, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Walter S. Robertson, Dean Rusk, Edgar Shannon, Jr., Adlai E. Stevenson, Kenneth Thompson, and Francis O. Wilcox. Much of the correspondence directly concerns Baldwin's career as an officer in the United States Foreign Service.
Organization
This collection is organized in three series: 1) Correspondence, 2) Speeches and Articles, arranged alphabetically by title and 3) Newsclippings and Printed Material.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
- Correspondence 1930-1982 (Box 1)
- Letter and Memorandum to Chester Bowles from C. F. Baldwin re Improving State Department Operations 1960 October 5 (Box 1)
- Letter and Remarks to J. W. Fulbright from C. F. Baldwin re foreign policy problems which resulted in "The Need For Better Foreign Policy Planning" 1959 February 9 (Box 1)
- Series II: Speeches and Articles
- An Ambassador's Journey An Exploration of People and Culture 1984 (Box 1)
- Addendum to An Ambassador's Journey [ca. 1984] (Box 1)
- "America and the World" n.d. (Box 1)
- The American Association of Singapore Luncheon Speech 1964 January 21 (Box 1)
- "American Foreign Policy New Myths and Old Realities" n.d. (Box 1)
- "American Foreign Policy-Retrospect and Prospect" n.d. (Box 1)
- "American Responsibilities in World Affairs" n.d. (Box 1)
- "America's Thorny Problems of Nationalism" n.d. (Box 1)
- "Asia and the West: A Diplomat's View" 1966 August 12 (Box 1)
- "The Automotive Market of Australia" 1929 (Box 1)
- "The Contemporary War" n.d. (Box 1)
- "Controversy in Southeast Asia" 1965 January 27 (Box 1)
- "Diplomacy" n.d. (Box 1)
- "A Dog's Life in the Foreign Service" n.d. (Box 1)
- "Economic Development and Political Evolution in Asia" in the Department of State Bulletin 1954 October-November (Box 1)
- "Economies of Non-Communist Asia" 1955 March 15 (Box 1)
- "The Far East-Mirror of American Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Foreign Policy and the American Character" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Incident in the Islands" n.d. (Box 2)
- "The Making of Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Malaysia-Aftermath of Colonialism in Southeast Asia" n.d. (Box 2)
- "The Myth as a Political Weapon" 1963 February 15 (Box 2)
- "The National Security Advisor-Obstacle in the Decision-Making Process" n.d. (Box 2)
- Oral History Interview with Charles Baldwin by Dennis J. O'Brien for the John F. Kennedy Library 1969 March 13 (Box 2)
- "Our Future Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "The Population Problem and American Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Public Opinion and American Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Requirements for and Effective American Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Some Reflections on American Foreign Policy" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Southeast Asia-Historical Resume" n.d. (Box 2)
- "Southeast Asia's Future-Subjugation or Cooperation" n.d. (Box 2)
- "The Third America and the World"-A speech given at the Independence Day Exercises at Monticello 1980 July (Box 2)
- "The Third America and the World"-A speech given at Joint House Committee on Social and Public Affairs n.d. (Box 2)
- "U.S. Foreign Policy An Estimate of the Situation" n.d. (Box 2)
- "United States Foreign Policy in the Changed World" n.d. (Box 2)
- "United States Foreign Policy Problems and Capacity" n.d. (Box 2)
- Vignette of Justice William Douglas n.d. (Box 2)
- Letter to the Editor, The Washington Post re the appointment of non-career persons to diplomatic posts 1985 July 31 (Box 2)
- Series III: Newsclippings, and Printed Material
- Newsclippings 1940-1983 (Box 2)
- Printed 1964-1981; & n.d. (Box 2)
- Zanesville School Calendar-contains a drawing of Washington's birthplace by C. F. Baldwin 1916 (Box 2)